十五年前，一个科学实验出了岔子，带来高智慧猿猴物种的        。
期间由猿猴流感衍生出的病毒，几乎摧毁了整个人类族群。
黎明
凭借凯撒的统领，新猿猴文明        初现。人类种族的幸存者只能奋力挣扎以求共存。
但因猿族叛徒科巴向人类展开复仇袭击，最终引发了战争。
人类向北面军事基地内集结的残余美国陆军发出紧急求救，
冷酷的特种部队上校和他的勇猛营士兵们受令去歼灭猿猴族。
传言指出凯撒在逃避追捕的近二年间，
身处于丛林中的秘密指挥基地组编战斗，随着        的肆虐…
猿猴
杀手
该闭眼了
也译作《君子红颜》(1951)：讲人类做实验让一只猩猩学习人类社会的道德观
猴崽子
濒危
物种
队长
Cap.
那是条战壕吗？
Is that a trench?
看起来里面好像还有更多的猴子
It looks like there's more of them inside.
回声 2-6 呼叫总部
Echo 2-6 to command.
上校 我们在树林北部发现三只猿类 一只持有武器
Colonel, we've got eyes on 3 kongs in the north woods. One of them is armed.
驴子刚发现了另一个战壕 它们的大本营可能就在附近
Our donkey just spotted another trench. Maybe the base is near.
遵命 长官
Yes, sir.
了解 长官 通话结束
Yes, sir. Copy. Over.
驴子过来
Donkey.
普里彻
Preacher.
你搞定那只有枪的
The one with the gun.
- 只要他击倒它 你们就马上把战壕轰了 - 遵命 长官
- As soon he guns him down, you guys take out the trench. - Yes, sir.Yes, sir.
开火！
Fire!
冲啊！
Come on!
装弹
Reload.
快撤！
Fall back!
上校 你听得到吗 上校？
Colonel, do you copy? Colonel?
- 你是谁 - 我是普里彻 长官
- Who is this?  - Preacher, sir. Preacher.
你在哪里?快告诉我你的坐标
Where are you, soldier?I need your position.
- 我不知道 - 你能看见什么吗？
- I don't know. - What do you see?
什么也看不见 我们损失惨重 小队长也阵亡了
I can't see anything, sir. We lost a lot of men and captain is dead, sir.
- 冷静 现在由你来指挥 - 我吗 长官
- Calm down. You're in command now. - Command, sir?
我觉得这只有我一个人了
I think it’s just me by myself now.
上校 我大概没有活路了
Colonel, I don‘t think I'm gonna make it, sir.
抱歉 长官 真的很抱歉
I am sorry. I am so sorry, sir.
听我说 那你能杀多少就杀多少
Listen to me. Kill as many as you can.
不 不 不！
No. No, no!
阵亡63人
63 dead.
就是你 你就是凯撒
You are him. You're Caesar.
我们找你找得好苦
We've been searching for you for so long.
我们听说你有个隐蔽的指挥所 但我们就是找不到
We heard you had a hidden command base, but we could never find it.
我们当中有些人 觉得你可能已经死了
Some of us were starting to think that you might be dead,
但麦卡洛上校说你没死 而是藏在某处
but the Colonel McCullough said you were out here somewhere.
- 要杀就痛快点 - 闭嘴！
- Just kill us already. - Shut up, man!
怎么了？它们就是一群畜生 它会宰了我们的
What? They're animals. He's gonna slaughter us.
这场战争不是我挑起的
I did not start this war.
罪魁祸首已经死了
The ape who did is dead.
他叫科巴
His name was Koba.
我已经处决了他
I killed him.
- 如今我只为保护猿族而战 - 是吗？
- Now I fight only to protect apes.  - Yeah?
那他呢？我们还有十多个那样的猿族
What about him? We got ten more just like him.
我认识他们 科巴的亲信
I know these apes. They followed Koba.
他们曾想杀了我
They tried to kill me.
他们害怕我的惩罚
They fear what I will do to them.
所以
So now
现在他们跟着你们
they serve you?
只是为了活命
just to survive.
我可不怕你
I no fear you!
你才应该害怕
You must fear!
你觉得你们还能在森林里藏多久？
How long you think woods can protect you?
人类能毁了你
Humans destroy you.
上校拥有至高无上的权力
Their Colonel has all power.
对这些人来说 他可不是个普通人
For them, he more than just human.
他就是神
He everything.
他说 先杀了凯撒
He say: "First Caesar die?
再让所有猴子给他陪葬
then all of you die."
温特 把这个叛徒带走
Winter! Take this traitor outside!
怎么处理这些人类？
What should we do with the humans?
你要放我们走？
You are letting us go?
告诉这位上校 你们见到我了
Tell your Colonel, you have seen me now.
替我传个话 只要他把森林留给我们
And I have a message for him. Leave us the woods?
一切杀戮就可以结束了
and the killing can stop.
你觉得他们会传话吗？
Do you think they will give him the message?
他们本身就传达了我的意思 毛里斯
They are the message, Maurice.
他会明白我们并不是什么野蛮动物
He will see we are not savages.
那个叛徒攻击了我！他跑了！
The traitor attacked me! He got away!
科巴真是阴魂不散
Koba still haunts us.
我之前没意识到 人类对他的所做所为 他有多么耿耿于怀
What I didn't see that he could not forgive what humans did to him.
没人知道他内心
No one could have known how much darkness...
有多阴暗
was living inside him.
父亲！
Father!
欢迎回家 火箭
Welcome home, Rocket.
你受累了
You look tired.
- 路途遥远 - 父亲 我们有发现！
- It was a long journey. - Father, we found something!
跟我来
Come.
母亲
Mother!
科尼利厄斯 快和你哥哥打个招呼
Cornelius... Say hi to your brother!
儿子 快看这是谁
Look who's here, son...
莱克
Lake...
就是这里 父亲 我们可以在这里建个新家园 重新开始
This is it, Father. We can start over. A new home.
- 儿子 那些山的另一边是什么？ - 给他们看看 火箭
- What is beyond those mountains, son? - Show them, Rocket.
一个沙漠！路途很遥远...
A desert! The journey is long...
所以人类不会找上门来的
But that is why humans will not find us.
我们必须今晚就离开！
We must leave tonight!
今晚？不可能
Tonight? That's impossible.
- 我们还能躲多久 莱克？军队快来了！ - 温特…
- How long can we wait, Lake? Soldiers getting closer! - Winter...
你儿子这段时间不在 凯撒...
Your son's been gone, Caesar...
他不知道我们的生活多艰难
He doesn't know how hard it's been.
我知道你很害怕
I know you are scared...
我们都怕
We all are...
但我们还是需要好好计划
But we are still planning...
对 我们要找到离开森林的安全路线
Yes. We must find a safe way out of woods.
之前只有你们俩
There were only two of you.
但是我们有很多同胞
But we are many.
我们会找到路线走出去的
We will find a way out of here.
猿族要团结起来才能强大
Apes together strong.
留在这 儿子 保护你妈妈和弟弟！
Stay here, son. Protect your mother and brother!
凯撒！怎么了？
Caesar! What's wrong?
有多少人在巡逻？
How many on patrol?
- 五六个人？- 集结起来！
- Five? Six? - Get them!
卢卡 叫上火箭
Luca, get Rocket too.
呼叫指挥部 上校...
Unit calling command. Colonel...
- 火箭？怎么了？- 我听见他说话了！上校在这里！
- Rocket? What happened? - I heard him talking! Colonel is here!
九十九号 目标已拿下
Ninety-nine, target acquired.
九十九号 目标已拿下 重复一遍 金刚已死
Ninety-nine, target acquired. Repeat, King Kong is dead.
我们走吧 我要从这里上去
Let's go. I get up from here.
凯撒... 我们找不到温特！
Caesar... We can't find Winter!
他之前吓坏了！我觉得他背叛了我们！
He was scared! I think he betrayed us!
你们找到科尼利厄斯了吗？
Have you found Cornelius yet?
我们还在找
We're still searching.
我们去找凯撒的小儿子吧
Let's go look for Caesar’s little son.
过来 科尼利厄斯
Come, Cornelius.
你已经安全了
You're safe now.
莱克
Lake.
既然你爱我的儿子
You loved my son.
那就照顾好他的弟弟 等我回来
Look after his brother, until I return.
你不和大家一起去我们的新家吗？
You're not coming with us to our new home?
不
No.
和莱克一起走
Go with Lake.
凯撒！你不是要去追他们吧?!
Caesar! You're not going after them?!
不是他们 是他
Not them, him.
凯撒 你是我们的首领！
Caesar, you are our leader!
我们不能没有首领自己走！
We can't leave without you!
必须这样
You must.
士兵们很快就会回来
The soldiers will be back soon.
爸爸！
Father!
等我找到他 所有士兵都会来追我
When I find him, the soldiers will all come after me.
那是你们离开森林的最好机会了
That makes you the best chance to get out of woods.
他去哪？！
Where is he going?!
凯撒！凯撒！
Caesar! Caesar!
那些士兵的营地总是不固定
The soldiers' camp is always moving.
我的卫兵们知道在哪能找到营地
My guards think they know where it is.
- 让我一起去 - 你需要我帮助你！
- Let me take you. - You need me to back you up!
不！
No!
拜托了... 我知道失去儿子的感受
Please... I know what it's like to lose a son.
我可能回不来了
I may not make it back.
所以我才要一起去
That's why I'm coming.
好让你可以回来
To make sure you do.
卫兵们觉得那些士兵在这里... 这里一直点着火
Guards think soldiers here... Always fires burning.
这里没有人
No one here.
搜索这片区域
Search the area.
先让我把这些放下
Just gonna put this down.
他一个人在这里干什么？
What's he doing out here alone?
也许他是个逃兵？
Maybe he's a deserter?
四处看看
Look around.
能拿的东西都尽量带走
Take what you can.
她有点不对劲 我觉得她不会说话
Something wrong with her. I don't think she can speak.
走吧
Come.
她自己一个人活不下去
She'll die out here alone.
我们不能带她走 毛里斯
We cannot take her, Maurice.
我明白... 但是我不能就这么扔下她
I understand... But I cannot leave her.
m 10 0 l 209.625 0 l 219.5 7.375 l 209.625 14.75 l 10 14.75 l 0 7.375 l 10 0
只有死了的金刚
才是好金刚
你发现上校了吗？
Did you find the Colonel?
没有
No.
温特
Winter.
上校在哪？
Where is the Colonel?
- 他走了 - 走了？
- He's gone. - Gone?
今天早上离开的 带走了很多人
He left this morning, took many men with him.
因为有更多的士兵要从北方过来
More soldiers are coming down from the North.
上校要去边境地带和他们汇合
The Colonel is going to meet them at the border.
什么边境？为什么？
What border? Why?
我不知道
I don't know.
但是我们这些剩下的人 明天也要走
But the rest of us are going tomorrow.
驴子们认为北方来的那些士兵
Donkeys think the soldiers from the North
是来援助军队 彻底铲除掉猿族
are coming to help finish off the apes for good.
那一天 山上那场战斗结束以后
That day, after the battle on the hill,
我们抓到的那个驴子答应我 如果我告诉他们你们藏在哪里
the donkey we caught promised me the Colonel would spare my life
上校就会饶我一命
if I told them where you were hiding.
原谅我！
Forgive me!
我儿子...
My son...
我妻子...
My wife...
都死了
are dead.
现在我们怎么办？
Now what do we do?
等士兵们离开的时候...
Wait till the soldiers go...
跟着他们找到上校
Follow them to the Colonel.
科巴？
Koba?
猿族不应该杀害猿族
Ape not kill ape.
士兵们动身了！
The soldiers are leaving!
他们停下了
They stopped.
他们在朝什么开火？
What are they shooting at?
我不知道
I don't know.
为什么他们要杀了你？
Why did they shoot you?
和她一样！
Like her!
他不会说话！
He cannot speak!
他的伤口都是致命的
He will die of those wounds.
卢卡
Luca.
士兵们都去哪了？！
Where did the soldiers go?!
温特说他们去了边境
Winter said they were going to a border.
是啊 但是在哪个方向？
Yes but which way is that?!
坏…猿
Bad... ape.
我是坏猿
Bad ape.
你是谁？
Who are you?
在这里干什么？
What are you doing here?
我觉得他看不懂手语
I don't think he understands.
我不认识他 他不是我们的人
I don't recognize him. He's not one of us.
这里只有你一个吗？
Are you alone here?
冷吗？
Cold?
她冷
Cold.
我看到女孩 以为你们是一帮人类
I see girl. I think you human.
但你们是猿 和我一样！
But you ape. Like me!
不 别动 放下
No, no. Put down.
- 你在这里待了多久了？ - 很久了 很久很久...
- How long have you been here? - Long time. Long... long time.
家
Home.
我以前的家
Old home.
塞拉动物园
你还有同伴吗？
Are there more like you?
- 动物园里的其他猿呢？ - 死了 全都死了
- More apes... from zoo? - Dead. All dead.
这么多年 人类生病了
Long time. Human get sick.
猿变聪明了
Ape get smart.
然后人类杀猿 但我没有被杀
Then human kill ape. But not me.
我跑了
I run.
- 你自学了开口说话？ - 我听人类说话
- You learned to speak? - Listened human.
“坏猿！”
"Bad ape!"
就是我
Bad ape.
别
No.
别乱碰
No touch.
那是我的东西
That's mine.
我没事
I'm okay.
不可思议…
Amazing...
我一直以为我们是唯一的一群
Always thought we were the only ones.
我还好奇 世界上还有更多
Wonder if there are more in the world?
像我们这样的猿吗？
More apes like us.
来 吃啊 吃
Here. Eat. Eat.
有新朋友了
New friends.
真是特殊的日子
Special day.
加利福尼亚边境
隔离设施
塔 岩 礁
你从哪里搞到这个的？
Where did you get this?
坏地方
Bad place.
很久以前我发现的 离开动物园后我去觅食
I find long time ago. After zoo I look for food.
我找到这个人类动物园
I find human zoo.
专门关病人
Zoo for sick.
高高的墙 生病的人类爬墙
Big walls. Sick human climb.
坏的人类杀人
Bad human kill.
后来所有人类都病了
And then all get sick.
都死光了 好久好久以前了
All dead now. Long time. Long time.
坏的人类？
Bad humans?
士兵吗？
Soldiers?
- 士兵 - 一个废弃的军事营地！
- Soldiers. - A deserted military camp!
就在边境上
On the border!
也许上校带着军队就是要去那里？
Maybe the Colonel and the troops are going there?
那里远吗？你能带我们去吗？
Is it far? Can you take us?
人类动物园？
Human zoo?
不！别去那里 我…
No! No go back there. I...
所有人都死了 我到这里来 这里很安全
Everyone dead. I come here. Very safe here.
绝不回去！不
Never go back! No!
- 求你了 你必须带我们去 - 不！
- Please. You must take us. - No!
不！我不带 我不带 不不不
No! Cannot take! Cannot take! No, no!
不行 看啊看啊
No! Look! Look! Look!
又下雪了 没法离开 必须留在这
More snow. Cannot go. Must stay.
你可以吃东西 休息 留下来 跟我一起
You eat, you rest, stay here. With me.
来 这个归你
Here. You keep.
归她了
She keep.
雪佛兰II
新星
诺 娃
这孩子…
Who is...
是谁？
child?
我不知道
I don't know.
但她是和你们一起的？
But she with you?
她无依无靠
She has no one else.
我看到你刚刚看她的眼神
I see you look at her just now.
看上去很难过
Look sad.
你有孩子吗？
You have child?
有一个
One.
另一个被人类杀了
The other was killed by human.
士兵吗？
Soldier?
我…
I...
有过孩子
Had child.
你觉得你能在人类动物园…
You think you will find him...
找到他吗？
at human zoo?
那个士兵？
Soldier?
我不知道
I don't know.
也许吧
Maybe.
那…
Then...
也许我可以带你去
Maybe I take you.
渴了
Thirsty.
她渴了
我渴了
Thirsty.
卢卡 跟我来 我们走近点
Luca, come. Let's go closer.
你留下保护他们
Keep them safe.
他们在干什么？
What are they doing?
我不知道
I don't know.
那边呢？是巡逻队吗？
What's that? A patrol?
马上没有人
I don't see riders.
不准动！
Hold it!
我发现他们朝这边来了
I saw them coming.
至少这次…
At least this time...
我保护了你…
I was able to protect you...
凯撒…
Caesar...
不能继续了
This must stop.
现在去加入其它猿的大部队还不迟
It's not too late to join the other apes.
我们不能回头！
We cannot turn back!
卢卡献出了他的生命
Luca gave his life.
求你了！
Please!
他们必须付出代价
They must pay.
你现在…
Now...
听上去就像科巴
you sound like Koba.
带你们来是个错误的决定
It was a mistake bringing you all.
这是我一个人的战斗
This is my fight.
我会独自完成的
I will finish this alone.
你们走吧 快
Go. Now.
去加入大部队
Join the others.
怎么回事？
What happened?
他们突然出现
They came out of nowhere...
袭击了我们
Attacked us.
我们以为他们会将我们全部杀掉
We thought they would kill us all...
但是上校阻止了他们
But the Colonel stopped them!
他的眼神里流露着疯狂
There was madness in his eyes!
他说要在我们死之前好好利用我们
He said they would use us, before we died!
然后他们就把我们都带到这儿来了
And they brought us all here!
利用你们？
Use you?
他们逼迫我们干活
They've been forcing us to work!
什么…
What...
让你们干什么样的活？
What kind of work?
等等 我的小儿子 他怎么样了
Wait. My little son is here.
格兰特
Grant...
李
and Lee.
惠林顿
Wellington...
和拿破仑
and Napoleon.
卡斯特
Custer
还有卧牛
and Sitting Bull...
你可能没看过什么书
You’re probably not much of a reader,
但这是一个伟大的时刻
but this is a big moment.
你躲哪儿去了？
Where were you?
我们完全是偶遇到了你的族群 真幸运
We came upon your herd. We got lucky.
我很惊讶 你居然没跟他们在一起
I was surprised you weren’t with them.
但愿你不会后悔放了他
I hope you don’t come to regret sparing his life.
他是个优秀的射手
He's quite a good shot.
你最终还是来救你的族人了吗？
Have you finally come to save your apes?
我是来找你的
I came for you.
找我？
For me?
那天晚上我杀的是谁？
Who did I kill that night?
我的妻子
My wife.
还有我的儿子
My son.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我本来是想杀你的
I was there for you.
我的天哪
God.
看看你的眼睛
Look at your eyes.
简直跟人类的眼睛一模一样
Almost human.
- 你是怎么找到这儿的 - 我收到消息 你会来这儿
- How did you know I was here?  - I was told you were coming.
北方的大部队
That more soldiers from the north...
- 会来这儿和你汇合 - 和我汇合？
- would be joining you here.  - Joining me?
为了把我们猿类
To finish us off.
赶尽杀绝
For good.
谁告诉你的？
Who told you that?
好吧
Okay.
我们走
Let's go.
爸爸！
Father!
莱克
Lake.
原谅他们吧 我们经历太多了
Forgive them. We've been through much.
爸爸！
Father!
我都做了什么？
What have I done?
全体 立定！
Battalion, halt!
- 鲜血！ - 滋养青草！
- Blood!  - Makes the grass grow!
- 我们！  - 可以献出鲜血！
- We!  - Make the blood flow!
- 我们既是开始！ - 也是终结！
- We are the beginning!  - And the end!
♫ 背景音乐：美国国歌《星条旗》♫
█████████████
●
易燃品
危险
AΩ：A代表Alpha阿尔法，Ω代表Omega欧米伽，分别是希腊字母的第一个和最后一个
开始和终结 AΩ
自从我们来了这儿 还没得到水和食物…
We haven't had food or water since we got here...
他们为什么要建这堵墙？
Why do they need a wall?
驴子！
Donkey!
- 教训他 – 好的
- Get him! - Okay, okay.
好的
Okay.
别再打了！
Leave him!
- 让他们回去继续工作 – 我们需要食物和水
- Tell them to get back to work. - Apes need food and water.
- 告诉他们 – 给他们食物和水
- Tell them. - Give them food and water.
五
Five.
四
Four.
三
Three.
二
Two.
快回去工作！
Hurry! Back to work!
把他绑起来 驴子
String him up, donkey.
坏地方
Bad place.
很坏 很坏的地方
Bad, bad place.
你看到了什么
What you see?
- 一定要救他们 – 怎么救？
- Must save them! - But how?
动动脑子 凯撒他会怎么做？
Must think! What would Caesar do?
啊！
No!
怎么这么小？
Why so small?
上校承诺了你什么？
What did the Colonel promised you?
你真以为他会放过你吗
You really think he let you live?
在我们都死了之后？
After we are gone?
你让他们叫你驴子
You let them call you donkey.
可你是猿类
You are ape.
上校要见你
Colonel wants see you.
历史
再敢妨碍他们干活
Interfere with the work again,
我就把他们一个个全都杀掉
I will begin slaughtering the apes, one by one.
听懂了吗？我需要那堵墙
Understand? I need that wall.
他们需要食物和水
Apes need food and water.
当任务完成后 我自然会给他们食物和水
They'll get food and water when they finish their work.
给他们食物和水
Give apes food and water.
- 否则任务没法完成 – 你太感情用事了
- Or they cannot finish it. - You know, you're very emotional.
你有什么资本跟我讨价还价？
What makes you think you’re in a position to make demands?
- 好了 我们走 – 大部队快到了
- Okay, let's go. - The soldiers who are coming here,
他们不是来和你汇合的 对吧？
they are not coming to join you, are they?
我看到外面那些士兵 在墙上准备作战
I saw men outside, on the wall, preparing for battle.
他们告诉我你很聪明 不过想不到这么聪明
They told me you're smart, but that's impressive.
对 他们不是来汇合的
No, they won't be joining me.
他们是你的敌人吗？
They are against you?
他们害怕我
They fear me.
为什么 因为你连自己人也杀吗？
Why? Because you kill your own men?
我们发现了尸体
We found bodies.
那几个人很不对劲
Something wrong with these men.
天哪 你真是让我大开眼界
Jesus Christ, you are impressive.
据你所知 你肯定觉得我不是好人
You paint quite a picture. What you must think of me.
我觉得你没有怜悯之心
I think you have no mercy.
你可是来杀我的
You came here to kill me.
难道你会对我有怜悯之心吗？
Were you going to show me mercy?
我放了你的人 这就是我的怜悯之心
I showed you mercy when I spared your men.
我提出了和平共处 可你却杀了我的家人
I offered you peace and you killed my family.
怜悯
Mercy.
你知道你的怜悯会让我们陷入怎样的境地吗？
Do you have any idea what your mercy would do to us?
你们比我们强壮
You’re much stronger than we are.
还那么聪明
You're smart as hell.
不管你怎么说 你们终将取代我们
No matter what you say, you’d eventually replace us.
这是自然的法则
That’s the law of Nature.
讽刺的是 是我们创造了你们
The irony is, we created you.
我们总是试着违背自然 征服自然
We tried to defy Nature, bend it to our will.
于是大自然开始惩罚我们的自以为是
And Nature’s been punishing us for our arrogance ever since.
十个月前 我派出了侦查小组去寻找你们的基地
Ten months ago, I sent out recon units to look for your base.
我的儿子就是这个小组的一员
My own son was a soldier with one of the units.
有一天他突然不能说话了
One day he suddenly stopped speaking.
他变得原始化 像动物一样
He became primitive, like an animal.
他们告诉我
They contacted me,
说他们觉得我儿子疯了
said that they thought he’d lost his mind,
因为承受不住战争的压力
that the war was too much for him.
后来负责照顾他的那个人也不会说话了
Then the man who cared for him stopped speaking too.
在小队的医务兵还能说话的时候 他提出了一个理论
Their medic had a theory, before he stopped speaking,
即使是幸存者身上也同样携带着
that the virus that almost wiped us out,
那让人类濒临灭绝的可怕病毒
the virus that every human survivor still carries,
病毒突变了
had suddenly changed.
变异了
Mutated.
如果它转播开来 人类将会彻底灭亡
And if it spread, it would destroy humanity for good this time.
不是杀死我们 而是会夺走我们之所以成为人类的核心
Not by killing us, but by robbing us of the things that make us human.
我们的语言 我们的高等思想
Our speech, our higher thinking.
它会把我们变成野兽 而你却在这儿跟我谈怜悯？
It would turn us into beasts. You talk about mercy?
换作你你会怎么做？
What would you have done?
当时有那么一刻我非常清醒
It was a moment of clarity for me.
我意识到我必须牺牲自己唯一的儿子
I realized that I would have to sacrifice my only son,
这样人类才能得以保全
so that humanity could be saved.
我握着那把枪很久很久
I held that gun in my hand for a long time...
我把它对着我唯一的孩子
And I pointed it at my only child.
他看着我 眼神里全是信任
He looked at me with trust in his eyes.
即使在他原始的眼神中
Even in his primitive gaze,
我也感受到了他的…
I felt his...
爱
love.
我扣动了扳机
I pulled the trigger.
我感觉被净化了 这使我的目标更加明确
It purified me. It made my purpose clear.
我下令杀掉其他所有被感染的人
I gave orders to kill the others infected, all of them.
烧掉他们任何能够传播病毒的东西
Burn their belongings, anything that might spread contamination.
有些手下质疑我的判断
Some of the men questioned my judgment.
我是在让他们去做和我一样的选择
I was asking them to do what I had done,
牺牲他们的朋友 家人
to sacrifice their friends, their family.
当然 他们拒绝了
Of course, they refused.
所以我把他们也杀了
I had them killed too.
其他带着孩子的偷偷逃进了树林里
Others with children deserted into the woods.
有一个懦夫 跑到了北方我的上级那里
One of those cowards fled to my superiors up north.
他们试图说服我
They tried to convince me
让我相信这场瘟疫可以通过医疗手段来解决
that this plague could be dealt with medically.
我意识到 在经历了这么多之后他们还是什么都没学到
That’s when I realized that they had learned nothing from our past.
你把他们也杀了？
You killed them too?
我是怎么做的来着 普里彻？
What did I do, Preacher?
你砍下了他们的脑袋 长官
You severed their heads, sir.
除了被我放走的那一个
Except for the one I spared
我让他回去替我捎个口信
so he could return and deliver a message.
如果他们想要卸下我的指挥权
If they wanted to relieve me of my command,
就得来这里找我 亲自动手
they’d have to meet me here, and do it themselves.
这里曾经是个军械库
This used to be a weapons depot.
在猿流感爆发初期 他们把这里改造成了一个集中营
They turned it into a relocation camp when the crisis was just beginning.
但是武器还在这里 就在山里面
But the weapons are all still here, inside the mountain.
他们会派多少人来？
How many men will be coming?
可能会倾巢出动
Probably all of them.
但别想太多
But don’t get any ideas,
除了我 他们最怕的就是你们猿类了
the only thing they fear more than me is you apes.
这是一场圣战
This is a holy war.
所有人类历史都指向这一时刻
All of human history has led to this moment.
如果我们输了 我们将成为最后的人类
If we lose, we’II be the last of our kind.
我们的地球会成为你们的猩球 而我们也会成为你们的牲口
It will be a planet of apes, and we’II become your cattle.
看看你
Look at you.
你觉得我疯了 对吧？
You think I am sick, don't you?
我其实并不想杀你儿子
I didn’t mean to kill your son.
但如果他注定会继承你的王位
But if his destiny was to inherit your unholy kingdom...
那我很欣慰我杀了他
I am glad I did.
回来！
Get back!
这么感情用事！
So emotional!
我知道你内心非常纠结
I see how conflicted you are.
你搞不清楚自己的目标
You are confused in your purpose.
你对我的所作所为感到愤怒 但这就是残酷的战争
You’re angry at me for something I did that was an act of war.
而现在你已经对此注入了太多的私人恩怨
But you’re taking this all much far too personally.
你好好想想 如果你杀了我
What do you think my men would have done to your apes,
我的人会怎么处置你的同类？
if you had killed me?
还是说杀了我对你来说更重要？
Or is killing me more important?
到处都是士兵 我们要怎么进去？
Soldiers everywhere! How will we get in?
得想办法进去 必须得进去！
Must get in somehow... Must get in!
进去？要进去？
In? In?
不行！
No!
不能进去！不能！
No go in! No!
朋友 朋友！不能进去！
Friends! Friends! No! No go in!
不能进去！
No go in!
朋友！朋友！
Friend! Friend!
谢谢 谢谢 朋友
Thank you. Thank you, friend.
你救了我们的命！
You save our lives!
此路
可逃出生天
患病的人类 肯定就是从这里逃走的
Sick humans must have escaped down here!
不 不！别爬！
No, no! No, no climb! No!
什么？你看到了什么？
What? What you see?
我们在哪里
Wonder where we are.
猿灾
泛滥
不！朋友
No! Friend...
不！
No!
不！不！
No! No!
不！回来 回来！
No! Come, come!
回来！回来 回来
Come! Come, come.
不！回来！
No! Come!
回来！回来！
Come! Come, come!
科巴...
Koba...
睡吧
Sleep.
你救不了他们的
You cannot save them.
猿类都将死在这里
Apes all die here.
- 不会的！- 会的
- No! - Yes.
跟我来...
Join me...
如果明早他还活着
If he's still alive in the morning...
就让他回去和其他猿类一起干活
He goes back to work as everyone else.
不然就杀了他
Or you shoot him.
快来 快来 快来
Come. Come. Come.
她进去了！
She go in!
渴吗？
Thirsty?
躲起来 快点
Hide. Quick.
那些人类会杀了她的！
Humans will kill her!
我知道怎么做 你们快走！
I know what to do! Go!
还有其他猿类在这吗？
Are there others out there?
去搜查下附近
Sweep the area.
把他押到围栏里去
Put him in the pen.
好点了吗？
Feeling better?
那就好 那我们可以计划下逃跑的事了
Good. Then we can talk about escape.
猩猩团结力量大！
Apes together strong!
- 我们既是开始！ - 亦是终结！
- We are the beginning! - And the end!
还活着呢
Still alive.
派他去采石场 就他一个
Send him to the quarry. Alone.
等等
Hold on.
这是什么？
What is this?
这东西怎么到这的？
How did this get in there?
带他去干活
Get him to work.
Thirty-seven.
Fifty-five.
走37步到大部队的笼子
Thirty-seven steps to the adult cage.
55步到孩子们的
Fifty-five to the children.
驴子
你明知道 等到墙建好了 上校就会杀了所有猿类
You know, Colonel shoot apes when wall is done.
这墙是疯狂之举
This wall is madness.
根本救不了他
It won't save him.
就像它也救不了你一样
Anymore than it will save you.
我自己会救我自己
I save myself.
你自己还剩什么值得去救的？
Is there anything left of you to save?
起来
Up!
大伙都回笼子里了吗？
Apes going back to the cage?
你真勇敢
You are very brave.
- 勇敢？ - 嗯 勇敢
- Brave? - Brave!
勇敢！
Brave!
猿类？
Ape?
我 是猿类吗？
Me? Ape?
你是…
You are...
诺娃
Nova.
来 来 快过来看看
Come! Come! Come to see!
过来看
Come to see!
来 快来看
Come! Come to see!
34，35，36，37！30！37！
34, 35, 36, 37! 30! 37!
我数好了
I do.
那现在怎么办？
What now?
什么？
What?
不！
No!
不 不  不 不！
No, no! No, no!
好吧
Okay.
这就是我跟你们说的那个同类！
This is the ape I told you about!
谢谢你
Thank you.
坏猿
Bad Ape.
我是坏猿
坏...坏猿
Bad... Bad Ape.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
我们不能再挖了 要不然整个隧道都会被淹了的！
We can't keep digging! It will flood the whole tunnel!
可是不继续的话 我们就够不到孩子们了啊！
If we don't, we can't reach the children!
m 10 0 l 209.625 0 l 219.5 7.375 l 209.625 14.75 l 10 14.75 l 0 7.375 l 10 0
把恐惧留给
自己
和他人
分享勇气
我们必须继续在这下面找路子...
We must keep looking down there...
再想想其他办法去孩子们那里
Find another way to reach the children.
我们现在必须马上离开 更多士兵就要来了！
We must leave now! More soldiers are coming!
人类要自相残杀 也会殃及我们的
Humans will destroy each other! And us with them!
那现在只能在地面上救孩子们出来了
We’II have to get the children out above ground.
怎么救？
How?
你们这些畜生！
You animals!
谁干的？
Who did that?
到底是谁？
Who was it?
是你吗？
Was it you?
我爱你 儿子
I love you, son.
走 快走
Go, go.
快点 我们走！
Hurry! Let's go!
凯撒 怎么了？
Caesar, what's wrong?
快走 你赶紧走
Hurry. You must go.
就你不走吗？
Without you?
不行
No.
毛里斯说的对
Maurice was right.
我现在就像科巴
I am like Koba.
他那时放不下仇恨
He could not escape his hate.
现在我也无法放下
And I still cannot escape mine.
走 快走 快走！
Move! Go, go! Go! Go! Go! Go!
上校！上校！
Colonel! Colonel!
他人到底在哪？
Where the hell is he?
快点！
Hurry up!
上校 你在里面吗 上校？
Colonel, are you in there? Colonel?
驴子 快去拿榴弹发射器！
Donkey! Grenade launcher!
该死的 驴子 把发射器给我拿来！
God damn it, donkey! Get me the launcher!
开始即结束
THE BEGINNING THE END
别担心
Don't worry.
毛里斯...
Maurice...
你们现在都到家了
You are home now.
猿类很强大
Apes are strong...
不管有没有我
With or without me.
儿子他会知道
Son will know...
谁是他的父亲
who was father.
还有
And what...
凯撒
Caesar did...
为我们做的一切…
for us.
凯撒…
Caesar...